i got a good amazon deal on this
birchwood kc perma blue
the label and instructions were in
spanish but i was able to find
english instructions pretty easily
online the application procedure
is the same as the super blue that i
have used successfully on several
projects
i chose an old nail set as my
demonstration piece
i try to pick up old punches when i see
them at yard sales and flea markets
i really dig the different knurling
patterns
i had previously finished a couple of
these with super blue
so i thought this would be a good way to
compare the two products
the knurling cleaned up nicely with the
wire wheel
the trick is to find the correct angle
to best clean out the tiny grooves
i used my belt sander to clean up the
flat surfaces
i was careful not to remove too much
material around the maker's mark
if the metal got too hot to hold with my
bare hands
i would dunk it in water to preserve the
temper
[Music]
i worked above the platen on the conical
section i also rounded the corners above
the platen
[Music]
here's the nail set after the wire wheel
and belt sander
i think i sanded down to 400 grit
[Music]
i cleaned the part with denatured
alcohol in my experience
you can't clean the part too much once
you think you have it cleaned
go ahead and wipe it down again
[Music]
after cleaning with the denatured
alcohol i rinse the part with tap water
i used a cotton ball to apply the
perma-blue
to the rinsed and dried part
[Music]
do
i let the bluing solution soak on the
part for about one minute
then i rinse the part in water
after drying the rinse part i lightly
buffed with super fine steel wool
i used a soft brass brush to buff the
knurling
[Music]
then i repeated the process to apply a
second coat
i would definitely recommend wearing
gloves when working with any chemical
like this bluing solution
i would also recommend using a fresh
cotton ball with each coat
and to avoid double dipping a dirty swab
into the bottle
after the second coat was buffed out i
soaked the part in oil
i used non-detergent 30 weight
i like to let the parts soak in oil at
least overnight
if not longer
[Music]
i like the 30 weight oil because it's
pretty thick
and clings to the part without drying
out
[Music]
here's the bridgeport 232nd nail set as
i found it at the yard sale
[Music]
and here's how it looks cleaned up and
blued with birchwood casey's perma blue
[Music]
the bluing came out pretty good i like
the color i achieved with two coats
[Music]
here's some photos comparing the perma
blue nail set
to a couple i finished with birchwood
casey's super blue
i think the perma blue compares well
with the super blue
[Music]
i would recommend giving either product
a try on your next project
[Music]
i hope you enjoyed the video thanks for
watching
[Music]
i had to promise chuck that we would
flit something
[Music]